{"tossups": [{"question": "The only time this man held political office was as Ulysses Grant\u2019s acting Secretary of War for seven weeks in 1869. After this man survived two bullet wounds at Shiloh, he was promoted to Major General. As he rampaged through the South, this commander employed \u201cscorched earth\u201d tactics to break the will of the Confederates, and captured Savannah as a \u201cChristmas present\u201d to President Lincoln. For ten points, name this Union leader who took Atlanta during his March to the Sea.", "answer": "William Tecumseh <b><u>Sherman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This remote territory was largely unaffected by the Protestant Reformation, although King Christian III established Lutheranism as the state religion. This country played host to the 1972 World Chess Championship between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer. This island nation, whose parliament is the oldest in the world, gained its independence from Denmark at the end of World War One. For ten points, what is this Nordic country, located just outside the Arctic Circle in the North Atlantic?", "answer": "<b><u>Iceland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In 2012, Australian Trent Grimsey set the record time for this action, completing it in 6 hours and 55 minutes. Thomas Gregory is the youngest person to have achieved this feat, doing so at 11 years old in 1988. In 2019, British cancer survivor Sarah Thomas became the first person to successfully complete this action four consecutive times. In 1926, Gertrude Ederle, the \u201cQueen of the Waves,\u201d became the first woman to complete, for ten points, what long-distance European swim?", "answer": "<b><u>Swim</u></b>ming the <b><u>English Channel</u></b> (accept descriptive answers including a <b><u>swim</u> </b>across the <b><u>English Channel</u></b>, prompt on answers including \u201cThe Channel\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Celeste Caiero\u2019s [[see-LESH-tee kuh-EYE-rohs]] actions during this event led to its popular name. A bridge spanning the Tagus [[TAY-gus]] River is named after the 25th of April, the date on which this event took place. This event began after Paulo de Carvalho\u2019s song written for Eurovision was played on a Lisbon radio station. For ten points, name this 1974 bloodless coup in which the Estado Novo was overthrown in Portugal, named for the flowers placed in soldiers\u2019 rifles after its success.", "answer": "<b><u>Carnation Revolution</u></b> (accept <b><u>25 April</u></b> Revolution until mentioned, accept synonyms for \u201cRebellion\u201d such as \u201cRevolution\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person\u2019s namesake charitable foundation was started after the Sociedad de Beneficencia refused her support due to her past career as an actress. A city built by that foundation was temporarily renamed Ciudad General Mart\u00edn Miguel de G\u00fcemes following a coup d\u2019etat which removed this woman\u2019s husband from power. The title \u201cSpiritual Leader of the Nation\u201d was given to, for ten points, what women\u2019s suffrage activist and supporter of the <em>descamisados</em>, a former First Lady of Argentina?", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> (accept <b><u>Evita</u></b> with or without surname)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A rebellion on this island was led by the cacique [[kuh-SEE-kay]] Enriquillo [[en-ree-KEE-yo]] and began after his father and other leaders were killed by Nicol\u00e1s de Ovando. The Spanish recognized French claims on this island through the Treaty of Ryswick. On this island, Christopher Columbus established the first European colony in the New World, La Navidad, though that colony was later destroyed by this island\u2019s Ta\u00edno people. For ten points, name this island that is today shared by Haiti and the Dominican Republic.", "answer": "<b><u>Hispaniola</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first of these episodes in recorded history was initiated by artisans working on the necropolis of King Ramses III. In 1894, Eugene Debs received a prison sentence when his constituents carrying out this action disobeyed a government injunction not to interfere with mail trains. One of these events ended in 1981 when the Reagan administration fired air traffic controllers involved in this action. For ten points, name these actions coordinated by employees who refuse to work.", "answer": "Labor <b><u>strike</u></b>s (prompt on descriptions of labor stoppages)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After this man dropped out of Reed College, he traveled India studying Zen Buddhism and seeking enlightenment. Joanna Hoffman helped market many of this man's products, one of which was named Lisa, and his employees included Andy Hertzfeld, who later founded General Magic. The mouse-driven gui [[GOO-EE]] of computers was taken over from Xerox by this man's company. Steve Wozniak and this man pioneered the personal computer revolution, producing Macintosh products. For ten points, name this co-founder of Apple, Inc.", "answer": "Steve <b><u>Jobs</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In a Klickitat legend, this geographical feature was formed when the chief of the gods transformed the beautiful maiden Loowit into a mountain. The first Europeans to spot this mountain were sailors aboard the HMS <em>Discovery</em>, commanded by George Vancouver. The Grateful Dead played \u201cFire on the Mountain\u201d at the Portland Memorial Coliseum as smoke poured from this nearby peak. For ten points, name this volcano in the Pacific Northwest, whose 1980 eruption killed 57 people.", "answer": "Mount <b><u>St. Helens</u></b> (or <b><u>Lawetlat\u2019la</u></b> or <b><u>Louwala-Clough</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This document warned of unrestricted submarine warfare in the Atlantic Ocean. This message suggested the \u201cimmediate adherence\u201d of Japan, and promised its recipient material assistance in recapturing territories lost in an earlier conflict. The intention of this coded message was to occupy the United States in a local conflict and keep it out of the war with Europe. For ten points, name this cable, intercepted in 1917, that contributed to the entry of the United States into World War One.", "answer": "<b><u>Zimmermann Telegram</u></b> (accept <b><u>Zimmermann Note</u></b>, accept <b><u>Zimmermann</u></b> <b><u>Cable</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "\"Puddler Jim\" Davis headed this department, employees of which included George Edmund Haynes, the first African-American to get a doctorate from Columbia University and the first director of the Division of Negro Economics. William Wilson was the first head of this department, and Louis Freeland Post conducted the Palmer Raids for it. This department is housed in the Frances Perkins Building, named for the first female cabinet member. For ten points, name this department that deals with laws governing unions and workplaces.", "answer": "U(nited) S(tates) Department of <b><u>Labor</u></b> (prompt on \"DOL\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These people could marry up in the <em>Lex canuleia</em>. After the second rebellion of these people, the Valerio-Horatian Laws were passed. Leaders of these people were forbidden from co-opting colleagues to vacant positions through the <em>Lex Trebonia</em>. These people got more power in the Publilian Rogation. These people were the lower class in the Conflict of the Orders, and they had their own Tribune to control Patrician power. The word plebiscite comes from a council for, for ten points, what commoner class in Rome?", "answer": "<b><u>Plebeian</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Pleb</u></b>s, prompt on \"commoners\" and similar answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Wool taxes to restore one of these structures led to legends that it was built on wool packs. The start of the pilgrimage trail to Canterbury began at one of these structures built in 1209. On that iteration of these structures, many buildings such as the Nonsuch House were located as were the displayed heads of traitors like William Wallace. Oilman Robert McCulloch brought a version of this structure to Lake Havasu City in Arizona. For ten points, by what name are all of these bridges across the Thames known, one of which is \"Falling down\"?", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b> Bridge", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Philip Sheridan claimed he often dropped off supplies for this man on the orders of President Andrew Johnson. Catholic clergy rights and the <em>fueros</em> were taken away in this man's namesake law. This man's administration created \"ports of deposit\" in the McLane-Ocampo Treaty. This man faced a war over his party's Plan of Ayutla, the Reform War. This man was a member of the Liberal party and succeeded Ignacio Comonfort as president. From a Zapotec origin in Oaxaca [[wah-HAH-kah]], for ten points, name this first indigenous Mexican president.", "answer": "Benito <b><u>Ju\u00e1rez</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Welshman Davy Gam was killed in this battle, during which nobles from Picardy and Artois were killed en masse. Taking tactics from the Battle of Nicopolis, the winners of this battle planted stakes for defense. Deep mud and heavy armor impaired one side at this battle, allowing for archers to cut down men-at-arms. Shakespeare\u2019s rendition of this Saint Crispin\u2019s Day battle included the \u201cBand of Brothers\u201d speech, given by this battle\u2019s victorious King Henry V of England. For ten points, name this 1415 battle during the Hundred Years' War.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Agincourt</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Richard Dobbs Spaight attacked this privilege in a correspondence with James Iredell. This privilege was set in state court via <em>Rutgers v. Waddington</em>. This privilege helps to counteract the \u201csword and the purse\u201d in Federalist 78. A case that instituted this privilege came about following the appointment of \"midnight judges.\" John Marshall used this ability to strike down part of a 1789 act in <em>Marbury v. Madison</em>. For ten points, name this legal doctrine which gives the Supreme Court the authority to rule a law unconstitutional.", "answer": "<b><u>Judicial Review</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Waldo Evans landed at this island's city of Piti. This island was captured by the USS <em>Charleston</em> under Henry Glass, and Spanish merchant Francisco Portusach helped surrender this island to the US. Masashi Ito and Soichi Yokoi hid on this island until the 1970s, long after this island was retaken from the Japanese in 1944. The Chamorro live on this island, part of the Mariana Islands, which was taken from Spain in the Spanish-American War. For ten points, name this US territory in the Pacific.", "answer": "<b><u>Guam</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This war included the Downes and Porter Expedition, as well as the Battle at Typee Valley. During this war, the navy attacked Polynesians at Nuku Hiva after Madisonville was founded. This war included the battle of Valparaiso in which David Porter captured the USS <em>Essex</em>. Besides its Pacific theatre, another campaign in this war included fighting at Lake Borgne and the Viller\u00e9 Plantation, during which Edward Pakenham engaged Andrew Jackson at New Orleans. For ten points, name this war which Fort McHenry's flag survived.", "answer": "<b><u>War of 1812</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>More than 1,200 people who took part in this event were interviewed by</u></b> <b><u>American journalist Isabel Wilkerson for her book</u> </b><em><b><u>The Warmth of Other Suns</u></b></em><b><u>. The</u></b> <b><u>Museum of Modern Art and The Phillips Collection co-own a 60-panel series titled for</u></b> <b><u>this event by \u201cdynamic (+)</u> cubist\u201d painter Jacob Lawrence. Like the earlier Exodusters movement, this ongoing movement led to the growth of northern neighborhoods like Bronzeville, Chicago. This (*) </b>mass exodus of African-Americans from the rural South to the urban North is known, for ten points, by what name?", "answer": "<b><u>Great Migration</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2012, this man was charged with stealing timber from the company</u></b> <b><u>Kirovles. This founder of \"The People\" movement had to pay millions in fines in the</u></b> <b><u>Yves Rocher case. This founder of the Anti-Corruption Foundation lost in a 2013</u></b> <b><u>election to Sergey (+)</u> Sobyanin. In an interview, this man called United Russia a \"party of crooks and thieves.\u201d While on a flight to Tomsk, this man was (*) </b>poisoned with the Novichok nerve agent. For ten points, name this Russian anti-corruption activist described as the \"man Vladimir Putin fears most.\"", "answer": "Alexei <b><u>Navalny</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This sect was defended in the Old Order Movement, and their Abecedarian</u></b> <b><u>sect rejected all learning. In the 1920s, this sect included the Bruderhof. Nicholas</u></b> <b><u>Storch, Thomas Dreschel, and Markus Stubner formed a trio that were the</u></b> <b><u>predecessors of this (+)</u> religious group. This group, which had the Schleitheim Confession and the Ausbund, was preceded by the Zwickau Prophets. Members of this group included Melchior Hoffan, Jacob Hutter, and (*) </b>Menno Simons, who names the Mennonites. For ten points, name this Protestant group that allowed for adult re-baptism.", "answer": "<b><u>Anabaptist</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Anabaptism</u></b>, antiprompt on \"Amish\" or \"Mennonites\" before mention)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's Sakalava people exchanged slaves for weapons with Omani</u></b> <b><u>Arabs. In a namesake charter, Joseph-Fran\u00e7ois Lambert was given control of all</u></b> <b><u>natural resources during the reign of Radama II, a king of this country's Merina (+)</u></b> <b>Kingdom. Several Christians were hurled off cliffs as part of this country's persecution of Christianity under queen Ranavalona I. This country's president Andry Rajoelina [[rah-djow-LEE-nah]] belongs to its (*) </b>Malagasy ethnic group. For ten points, name this island country which the French took over during the invasion of Antananarivo.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Madagascar</u></b> (or <b><u>Merina</u></b> Kingdom; or Kingdom of <b><u>Imerina</u></b>; or Kingdom of <b><u>Madagascar</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Cities that have hosted this event include San Diego, Newport, New York City,</u></b> <b><u>and Valencia, Spain. This event was first held near the location of Queen Victoria\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>final home, Osborne House, at East Cowes. A trophy awarded to one (+)</u> club that earns the right to participate in this event has, since 1983, been named for Louis Vuitton. Harold Vanderbilt, Ted Turner, and Larry Ellison have earned this trophy, which was won by a US (*) </b>skipper for 126 consecutive years. For ten points, name this oldest international sporting trophy, named after a schooner, not a country.", "answer": "<b><u>America\u2019s Cup</u></b> (or the <b><u>Auld Mug</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man became an army lieutenant in 1878, at the age of 14, and was made</u></b> <b><u>Inspector General of the Armed Forces in 1913. In 1889, this man\u2019s cousin Rudolf</u></b> <b><u>took his own life in a suicide pact with his mistress, leaving this man (+)</u> second in line for the throne. On the condition that his descendants would be excluded from the line of succession, this man was permitted to marry Countess (*) </b>Sophie Chotek in 1899. For ten points, name this Archduke whose assassination at the hands of Gavrilo Princip precipitated the First World War.", "answer": "Archduke <b><u>Franz Ferdinand</u></b> of Austria", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Languages in this family are not usually written by their native speakers but</u></b> <b><u>have used the Roman alphabet when they are written since the late 16th century. In</u></b> <b><u>1975, a South American government adopted a new orthography for this language</u></b> <b><u>family which uses five vowels (+)</u> rather than the traditional three. Due to the spread of this language family, it blended with other indigenous languages, such as Aymara, and influenced dialects of (*) </b>Spanish. For ten points, name this South American indigenous language family, spoken by the Inca.", "answer": "<b><u>Quechua</u></b>n language(s) (or <b><u>Runasimi</u></b>, accept <b><u>People\u2019s Language</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man\u2019s travels with US Army surgeon John Emerson took him to the free</u></b> <b><u>state of Illinois and the free territory of Wisconsin. This man, who died of</u></b> <b><u>tuberculosis in 1858, worked as a porter at a St. Louis hotel after then-State Senator</u></b> <b><u>Taylor Blow (+)</u> manumitted him in 1857. The legal arguments produced in this man\u2019s freedom suit were later adopted by (*) </b>Abraham Lincoln and influenced the creation of the Emancipation Proclamation. For ten points, name this man, whose landmark US Supreme Court case ruled the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional.", "answer": "Dred <b><u>Scott</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country possibly tried to ally with Muhammad al-Nasir of the Almohads</u></b> <b><u>according to Matthew Paris. A \u201ccrouchbacked\u201d prince from this country was almost</u></b> <b><u>made king of Sicily. A noble in this country, surnamed de (+)</u> Clare and nicknamed \"the Strongbow,\" invaded Ireland. This country was ruled by the (*) </b>Plantagenets, and it faced two Barons' Wars. This country was once ruled by a \"Softsword king.\u201d For ten points, name this country that borders Wales and Scotland.", "answer": "<b><u>England</u></b> (accept <b><u>Britain</u></b>, accept <b><u>Great Britain</u></b>, do not accept or prompt on \"United Kingdom\" or \"UK\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}